Dylan Pieper

Data Scientist and Social Psychologist

Profile

I develop data science solutions that build community, improve health and well-being, and support social change. Using R and Python, I build tools that translate data into insight—through descriptive analytics, statistical modeling, geospatial mapping, and web application and API development. I take a human-centered approach with crossfunctional teams to balance impact with scalability. My curiosity inspires me to explore new technologies in machine learning and contribute to open-source communities.

Personal Information

Madison, Wisconsin dylanpieper@gmail.com https://dylanpieper.github.io/

Professional Skills

Data Science Core

R, R Markdown, Quarto, Shiny

Database Architecture

MySQL, PostgreSQL, DuckDB

Data Engineering & DevOps

GitHub, Docker, APIs, Azure, Linux (RHEL)

Large Language Models

Claude, Claude Code, OpenAl, Ollama, DeepSeek

Research & Evaluation Tools

Tableau, Qualtrics, REDCap

Front-End Development

React, Bootstrap, Observable, SurveyJS

Transferable Skills

Statistics (NHST and Bayes), Object-Oriented Programming, Functional Programming, Package Development

Experience

Data Scientist - Program Evaluation and Research Unit (PERU), University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA

Sep 2021 - Present

- Lead data science initiatives for substance use treatment, public health, and justice reform projects
- Direct data strategy with cross-functional teams including healthcare providers, implementation teams, researchers, and IT departments
- Support supervision of a team of 3–5 analytics staff, including recruitment, professional development, and technical mentorship
- Design and implement data pipelines integrating data from 250+ healthcare sites
- Architect and maintain SQL databases that integrate health records, multiple tracking systems, and rich geographic and operational data
- Develop ETL workflows using R and SQL to automate data processing and reduce manual errors
- Engineer automated reports, web applications, and dashboards for healthcare providers and researchers deployed on university servers
- Evaluate data collection instruments through psychometric methods and pilot studies
- Build advanced statistical models using mixed-effect regression and survival analysis methods
- Author peer-reviewed research manuscripts, technical documentation, and data governance protocols

Experience

Field Interviewer - NORC at the University of Chicago, Chippewa Falls, Wisconsin

Aug 2021 - Nov 2021

- Conducted in-person interviews with research participants, recording responses using standardized survey instruments and protocols
- Traveled to various locations within an assigned geographic area to complete interviews, managing my schedule while meeting individuals for data collection
- Maintained confidentiality of all participant information and adhered to strict research ethics and data security procedures

Research Specialist - Michele Gelfand's Culture Lab, University of Maryland, College Park, MD

Aug 2020 - Aug 2021

- Analyzed and published data on COVID-19 deaths across 57 countries and their relationship to social norms using multilevel statistical models
- Ran two experiments testing different nudges, or message framing effects, for wearing masks and forecasted the utility of these interventions
- Developed a natural language processing (NLP) Shiny app to detect threatening language and compare levels across texts (https://www.michelegelfand.com/threat-dictionary)

Writing Coach - University of Northern Iowa, Cedar Falls, IA

Aug 2017 - May 2020

- Coached students in writing (CRLA certified) and statistics, providing personalized guidance to meet their needs and improve their academic performance
- Supported English Language Learners (ELLs) in improving their writing skills and language proficiency
- Coached students from diverse and non-traditional backgrounds, including students with learning disabilities
- Trained new tutors and designed comprehensive training materials to ensure effective tutoring practices
- Delivered lectures on academic integrity, plagiarism prevention, and essay writing
- Conducted outreach initiatives in classrooms and at student registration events to promote tutoring services and academic resources

Education

Master of Arts - Social Psychology - Unviersity of Northern Iowa, Cedar Falls, Iowa

2018 - 2020

- Thesis: "Challenging Social Systems Under the Threat of Pollution" (https://scholarworks.uni.edu/etd/1028/)
- Completed courses Statistical Computing I and II to learn base R
- Worked as a Research Assistant in the Psychoneuroendocrinology Lab
- Worked as a Teaching Assistant in undergraduate psychology courses (Introduction to Psychology, Biopsychology, and Psychology of Gender)
- Awarded research and travel funds from the university totaling \$1,800

Bachelor of Arts - Psychology - University of Northern Iowa, Cedar Falls, Iowa

2014 - 2018

Publications

- **Pieper, D. J.**, McNeill, J. M., Chirdon, C. R., Moore, D. W., Wang, E.-H., Raby, S., & Cloutier, R. M. (in preparation). Racial disparities in Pennsylvania's criminal justice system: Analyzing prosecutorial and judicial decision-making.
- Gelfand, M. J., Jackson, J. C., Pan, X., Nau, D., Pieper, D., Denison, E., Dagher, M., Van Lange, P. A. M., Chiu C., & Wang, M. (2021). The relationship between cultural tightness-looseness and COVID-19 cases and deaths: A global analysis. *The Lancet: Planetary Health*. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30301-6
- Gelfand, M. J., Li, R., Stamkou, E., Denison, E., Fernandez, J., Choi, V., Chatmen, J., Jackson, J. C., Pieper, D., & Dimant, E. (2021). Persuading conservatives and liberals to comply with mask-wearing: An intervention tournament. *Journal of Experimental Social Psychology*. https://doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.jesp.2022.104299
- Dimant, E., Clemente, E. G., **Pieper, D.**, & Azevedo, F. (2022). Politicizing mask-wearing: Predicting the success of behavioral interventions among Republicans and Democrats in the U.S. *Scientific Reports*, 12, 7575. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-10524-1
- **Pieper, D.** (2020). Challenging social systems under the threat of pollution: Replication and extension of Eadeh and Chang (2019) (Publication No. 1028) [Master's thesis, University of Northern Iowa]. *UNI ScholarWorks*. https://scholarworks.uni.edu/etd/1028

R Packages

- **redquack**: Transfer REDCap data to DuckDB with minimal memory overhead, designed for large datasets that exceed available RAM (https://dylanpieper.github.io/redquack/)
- **hellmer**: Batch process chats for large language models supported by ellmer (https://dylanpieper.github.io/hellmer/)
- **samesies**: Compare lists of texts, factors, or numerical values to measure their similarity (https://dylanpieper.github.io/samesies/)
- **shinysurveyjs**: Integrate SurveyJS with Shiny to interface with a PostgreSQL database and create dynamic survey experiences (https://dylanpieper.github.io/shinysurveyjs/)